{"tossups": [{"question": "This war\u2019s French theater included a victory for the Duc d\u2019Enghien [\u201dduke\u201d don-GYEN] at the Battle of Rocroi [roh-CWAH]. The Bohemian phase of this war ended with the Battle of White Mountain and the defeat of the Winter King. Wallenstein and the Count of Tilly served as Imperial generals during this war, in which Gustavus Adolphus was killed. The Peace of Westphalia ended, for ten points, what war fought over religion in modern-day Germany that lasted from 1618 to 1648?", "answer": "<b> Thirty Years</b>\u2019 War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this magazine that is famous for featuring single people on its cover, featuring a bright red border.", "answer": "<b> Time</b> Magazine", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Margaret Thatcher claimed to have carried a copy of this man\u2019s most famous work in her handbag at all times. This thinker rejects the \u201cbenevolence of the butcher, baker, and brewer\u201d as the reason that dinner is expected and, in his most famous work, describes a metaphor about the unintended social benefits of private, selfish actions as the \u201cinvisible hand.\u201d For ten points, name this Scottish \u201cFather of Economics,\u201d the author of<em> The Wealth of Nations</em>.", "answer": "Adam<b> Smith</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "This modern-day nation was dominated by the Chola Dynasty until its liberation by Vijayabahu I, who re-established Buddhism. Its native Kingdom of Kandy was dominated by the Dutch and conquered by the British, who grew tea in their colony of Ceylon. The majority Sinhalese fought with the Tamil Tigers on, for ten points, what island off the coast of India?", "answer": "<b> Sri Lanka</b> (accept<b> Ceylon</b> until mention)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The \u201cBuena Vista Tract\u201d in this city features streets named for Mexican War generals. To make room for this city\u2019s Civic Arena, many blocks of its African-American Hill District were demolished. This city\u2019s Point State Park preserves the site of a fort that was targeted by General Braddock in the French and Indian War. Fort Duquesne [do-kane] was built at the confluence of the Monogahela and Allegheny Rivers in what is now, for ten points, what city in western Pennsylvania?", "answer": "<b> Pittsburgh</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The production of this item names a group of 18th century nationalist revolutionaries in Italy. During the Industrial Revolution, the complete deforestation of Britain may have been prevented when blacksmiths replaced this item with coke. A companion company founded by Henry Ford produced this good out of byproducts from its car manufacturing; that company is now called Kingsford. For ten points, name this hot-burning, wood-based, solid carbon fuel, commonly used in blacksmith forges and barbecue grills.", "answer": "<b> charcoal</b> (prompt on Carbonari)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler resolved territorial disputes with Nader Shah by signing the Treaty of Resht and failed to form an alliance with William III. This man employed Patrick Gordon to capture Azov, which he later gave back to Ahmed III. He gave civil service a structured hierarchy via the Table of Ranks as part of an effort to reform the bureaucracy, and he disbanded the streltsy. The boyars lost both political power and their beards under the reign of, for ten points, what \u201cGreat\u201d modernizing tsar of Russia?", "answer": "<b> Peter the Great</b> or<b> Peter I</b> (prompt on Peter)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One war in this state began with an attack on Fort Myers, while another was triggered by the Dade Massacre. This state, purchased as part of the Adams-Onis Treaty, was home to a Native American tribe led by Osceola that fought Winfield Scott and Andrew Jackson. The Seminole Wars were fought in, for ten points, what southern U.S. state where the Spanish founded St. Augustine on the peninsula and Pensacola on the panhandle?", "answer": "<b> Florida</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was nearly assassinated at the funeral of Warren Davis by Richard Lawrence. Under this president, the US debt was paid off for the only time in history. This president had Levi Woodbury require government land to be bought with gold or silver in the Specie Circular, and he created \u201cpet\u201d banks after a veto. This man decried a \u201ccorrupt bargain\u201d that he claimed cost him the Election of 1824. For ten points, name this seventh President of the United States.", "answer": "Andrew<b> Jackson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Marco Antonio Bragadin was flayed alive after surrendering Famagusta in the name of this city. This city\u2019s Arsenale [ar-seh-NAH-lay] was said to be able to produce a warship a day, helping it repel multiple Ottoman invasions of Corfu. This city ruled over Crete after its leader, Enrico Dandolo, sacked Zara and agreed to provide transportation for the Fourth Crusade. For ten points, name this Queen city of the Adriatic, an Italian city known for its many canals.", "answer": "Most Serene Republic of<b> Venice</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The winning side of this match lit the cauldron in the opening ceremony of the 2002 Olympic Games. Marc Johnson tied this match, causing the other side to pull Vladislav Tretiak, its goalkeeper, after the first period. This game earned its name from a question asked by announcer Al Michaels in its final seconds. The winner of this match went on to defeat Finland to clinch the gold medal. For ten points, name this 1980 event in which the underdog United States defeated the Soviet Union in ice hockey at the Olympics.", "answer": "the<b> Miracle on Ice</b> (accept descriptive answers involving the match between the<b> United States</b> and the <b>Soviet Union</b> in the<b> 1980</b> Winter Olympics before \u201cUnited States\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s ruler was greatly embarrassed by the revelation of Philipp zu Eulenburg\u2019s [oy-len-burg\u2019s] homosexuality. This country sent a gunboat to its rival\u2019s territory in Morocco, causing the Agadir Crisis. Its high command was led by Helmuth von Moltke, and it was accused of sending the Zimmerman Telegram, causing the United States to declare war on this country. Kaisers led, for ten points, what member of the Central Powers, an empire that invaded France during World War I?", "answer": "<b> Germany</b> (or<b> German</b> Empire; accept<b> Second Reich</b> or<b> Kaiserreich</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Atlantic provinces of this kingdom were lost to the Great Fulo. This kingdom was founded after the defeat of Sumanguru at the Battle of Kirina and was succeeded by a dynasty led by Askia the Great. This kingdom\u2019s capital was Niani, the birthplace of its founder, Sundiata Keita. In 1324, one of its leaders was so generous with his spending that he devalued gold in Egypt. For ten points, name this West African kingdom ruled by Mansa Musa.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Mali</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Xu Bing used this art form to create the nonsensical</b><em><b> Book From the Sky</b></em><b>. Naskh and kufic are two forms of this art used by Muslim artists. This type of art was practiced on (+) </b> <b>tortoise shells in Shang dynasty China. Alcuin created one form of this technique known as the Carolingian miniscule. This technique is combined with (*)</b> painting and illustration to create illuminated works like the Lindisfarne Gospels and Book of Kells as well as for transcribing the Quran. For ten points, name this visual art of elaborate decorative writing.", "answer": "<b> calligraphy</b> (prompt on writing before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This ruler chartered the Levant Company in an attempt to form a trade alliance with the Ottoman Empire. This ruler supported the Netherlands through the Treaty of Nonsuch and attacked their enemy at Cadiz with the help of privateer (+) Francis Drake. During the Tilbury speech, this ruler declared that she had the \u201cbody of a weak and feeble woman\u201d but the \u201cheart and stomach\u201d of a king while rallying her men against the (*)</b> Spanish Armada. For ten points, name this daughter of Anne Boleyn who succeeded her sister Mary I to become the \u201cVirgin Queen\u201d of England.", "answer": "<b> Elizabeth I</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this work, a monk compares the tragedies of Lucifer, Hercules, Nero, and Julius Caesar, among others. Earlier in this work, an old hag notes that \u201csovereignty over their (+) husbands\u201d is what women want most, as described by the Wife of Bath. This work was unfinished at its author\u2019s death, including just 24 (*) </b> stories after the General Prologue, which introduces a group of pilgrims at the Tabard Inn on their way to visit the shrine of Thomas a Beckett, an Archbishop who was slain in 1170. For ten points, name this 14th century collection of stories written by Geoffrey Chaucer.", "answer": "The<b> Canterbury Tales</b> Page 9", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This composer\u2019s Adagio and Rondo was written for an ensemble that included Benjamin Franklin\u2019s glass armonica. His final three string quartets were written for Friedrich Wilhelm</b> <b>II of (+)</b> <b>Prussia, and his eleventh piano sonata ends with an imitation of Janissary bands</b> <b>from the Ottoman Empire. The impresario Johann Peter Salomon gave this man\u2019s forty-first and (*)</b> final symphony the nickname<em> Jupiter</em>. K\u00a8ochel [ker-kel] numbers are used to catalogue the works of, for ten points, what composer of the \u201cRondo alla Turca\u201d and<em> Eine Kleine Nachtmusik</em>?", "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus<b> Mozart</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>The first draft of this document was written by John Dickinson, who chaired an attempt to fix this document at Annapolis. The eleventh section of this document promised Canada</b> <b>automatic (+)</b> <b>admission, should they wish to join the United States. This document left</b> <b>the government unable to deal with (*)</b> Shays\u2019 Rebellion, since it denied Congress the power to levy taxes or maintain an army. For ten points, name this predecessor to the U.S. Constitution, a document that provided for a weak federal government.", "answer": "<b> Articles of Confederation</b> and Perpetual Union Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}